Guide to the Ivy Group Presidents Records
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Ivy Group Presidents records
1963-1977
RU 17
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
5.25
(10 boxes, 1 folio)
The records include the original agreement establishing the group in 1954; meeting agendas, outlines, and background materials; comprehensive files on intercollegiate athletics; documents outlining policy discussions and decisions on academic scholarships and admissions; the Ivy Group charter and handbook, 1972; and materials on Yale University's dispute with the National Collegiate Athletic Association (NCAA) over the Jack Langer case. The Ivy Group Presidents formed in 1954 to foster amateurism in collegiate athletics. Soon after, the organization broadened its mission and began meeting regularly to discuss educational philosophy and to formulate policies governing Ivy League academics, athletics, admissions, and scholarships.
Yale University. President's Office
General note
Forms part of Yale Record Group 2-A (YRG 2-A), Records of the President.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The records were transferred from the Office of the President, 1977 and 1980.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Arrangement
The records are arranged alphabetically by subject.
Scope and Contents
The records include the original agreement establishing the group in 1954; meeting agendas, outlines, and background materials; comprehensive files on intercollegiate athletics; documents outlining policy discussions and decisions on academic scholarships and admissions; the Ivy Group charter and handbook, 1972; and materials on Yale University's dispute with the National Collegiate Athletic Association (NCAA) over the Jack Langer case. The Ivy Group Presidents formed in 1954 to foster amateurism in collegiate athletics. Soon after, the organization broadened its mission and began meeting regularly to discuss educational philosophy and to formulate policies governing Ivy League academics, athletics, admissions, and scholarships.
College sports; Council of Ivy Group Presidents; Yale University -- Sports; Yale University. President's Office
- Records, Series I
  - 1973-1977 (Box 1, Folder 1-7)
  - 1976-1977 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Admissions, 1972-1973 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Athletic Association
    - Administration Committee, 1964-1975 (Box 2, Folder 10-12)
    - Admissions Officers Committee, 1965-1967 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Agreement of 1954: permanent file, 1954 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Coordination and Eligibility Committee
      - 1964-1967 (Box 2, Folder 15-16)
      - 1968-1974 (Box 3, Folder 17-18)
    - Correspondence, 1969-1974 (Box 3, Folder 19-20)
    - Meetings, 1970-1972 (Box 3, Folder 21-26)
    - National Collegiate Athletic Association (NCAA)
      - 1963-1967 (Box 4, Folder 27-35)
      - 1967-1969 (Box 5, Folder 36-40)
      - By-laws for scholarships, 1967-1968 (Box 5, Folder 41-42)
      - Correspondence, 1971-1974 (Box 6, Folder 43-48)
      - Infractions, Committee on the Jack Langer case, 1969-1970 (Box 6, Folder 49-51)
      - Policy Committee
        - 1963-1964 (Box 6, Folder 52)
        - 1963-1974 (Box 7, Folder 53-60)
    - Problems of Athletics, Committee on, 1970-1974 (Box 7, Folder 61)
    - Tuition policy, 1963-1965 (Box 7, Folder 62)
    - University Club, 1973 (Box 7, Folder 63)
  - Information on government relations, 1973 (Box 8, Folder 64-67)
  - Ivy Group Handbook, 1972 (Box 9, Folder 68)
  - Meetings
    - 1973-1974 (Box 9, Folder 69-74)
    - Materials, 1972-1974 (Box 10, Folder 75-78)
    - Notebook for agenda, 1973 (Box 10, Folder 79)
  - Names and addresses for correspondence, 1976 (Box 10, Folder 80)
  - Research Libraries Group: "Four Major American Libraries [New York Public, Harvard, Yale, and Columbia Universities] Announce Plan to Provide Better Service for Scholars," 1974 Feb (Box 10, Folder 81)
  - Oversize: Academic ranking of football freshmen and lettermen [includes: minutes of the Ivy Group Committee on Coordination and Eligibility, 1966 Sep 21, removed from: Athletic Association: Policy Committee, 1966], 1965-1966 (Box 11, Folder 82)